Dick Gackenbach Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Dick Gackenbach Papers.
1974-1991.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Gackenbach, Dick.
15 linear feet.
Dick Gackenbach was born 9 February 1927, in Allentown, PA, the son of William and Gertrude (Reichenbach) Gackenbach. He attended Jameson Franklin School of Art, NY, and Abbott School of Art, Washington, DC. He worked for J. C. Penney Company (New York City, 1950-1972) as a paste-up artist and later, creative director. He went out on his own as a free-lance author and illustrator beginning in 1972 to the present. Mr. Gackenbach died in 2001.
MSS19920043
Biography
Dick Gackenbach was born 9 February 1927, in Allentown, PA, the son of William and Gertrude (Reichenbach) Gackenbach. He attended Jameson Franklin School of Art, NY, and Abbott School of Art, Washington, DC. He worked for J. C. Penney Company (New York City, 1950-1972) as a paste-up artist and later, creative director. He went out on his own as a free-lance author and illustrator beginning in 1972-2001. He has also served as a consultant on art education for children with learning disabilities (1988-2001). Mr. Gackenbach died in 2001.
Scope and Content
The collection includes manuscripts, dummies, sketches, and original artwork for 21 books and one audio cassette.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
About the Author:
BOOKS
Wilson. Fifth Book of Junior Author and Illustrators, 1983. pp. 118-19
Marquardt, Dorothy A. and Martha E. Ward. Authors of Books for Young People, Supplement to the 2nd edition, Scarecrow, 1979.
PERIODICALS
Bulletin of the Center for Children's Books, February 1985; February 1987; April 1988.
Juvenile Literary Guild (brochure), April-September 1988.
New York Times Book Review, May 1 1977, pp. 29, 43; December 9 1979; February 22 1981, p. 31.
Publishers Weekly, October 28 1974, p. 48.
School Library Journal, November 1977, pp. 46-47; August 1988, p. 80.
Times Literary Supplement, March 30 1984, p. 339.
Source: Contemporary Authors Online. The Gale Group, 1999.
WRITINGS BY THE AUTHOR: FOR CHILDREN; SELF-ILLUSTRATED
(CLC call number will follow title if held in the Northeast Children's Literature Collection, listed alphabetically by title.)
A Bag Full of Pups, Clarion Books, 1981.
Alice's Special Room, Houghton, 1991.
Annie and the Mud Monster, Lothrop, 1982.
(Adapter)Arabella and Mr. Crac:An Old English Tale, Macmillan, 1982.
Beauty, Brave and Beautiful, Houghton, 1990.
Binky Gets a Car, Clarion Books, 1982.
Claude and Pepper, Seabury, 1976.
Claude Has a Picnic, Clarion, in press.
Claude the Dog: A Christmas Story, Seabury, 1974.
Crackle Gluck and the Sleeping Toad, Seabury, 1979.
Do You Love Me?, Seabury, 1975. C561
The Dog and the Deep Dark Woods, Harper, 1984.
Dog for a Day, Clarion, 1987.
Harry and the Terrible Whatzit, Seabury, 1977.
Harvey the Foolish Pig, Ticknor & Fields, 1988.
Hattie Be Quiet, Hattie Be Good, Harper, 1977. B101
Hattie Rabbit, Harper, 1976. B151
Hattie Rabbit, HarperCollins Children's Books, 1990.
Hattie, Tom and the Chicken Witch: A Play and a Story, Harper, 1980.
Hound and Bear, Seabury, 1976.
Hurray for Hattie Rabbit!, Harper, 1986. B13
Ida Fanfanny, Harper, 1978. C267
King Wacky, Crown, 1984. Not CLC B3929
The Leatherman, Seabury, 1977. C410
Little Bug, Clarion Books, 1981.
Mag the Magnificent, Clarion Books, 1985.
McGoogan Moves the Mighty Rock, Harper, 1981.
Mighty Tree, Harcourt, 1992.
More From Hound and Bear, Clarion Books, 1979.
Mother Rabbit's Son Tom, Harper, 1977. B88
Mr. Wink and His Shadow Ned, Harper, 1983.
Pepper and All the Legs, Seabury, 1978. B92
(Reteller) The Perfect Mouse, Macmillan, 1984.
The Pig Who Saw Everything, Seabury, 1978.
Poppy the Panda, Clarion Books, 1984.
(Adapter) The Princess and the Pea, Macmillan, 1983. C299
Supposes, Harcourt, 1989.
(Adapter)Timid Timothy's Tongue Twisters, Holiday House, 1986.
What's Claude Doing?, Clarion Books, 1984.
With Love from Gran, Houghton, 1989. C102
ILLUSTRATOR
Barbara Isenberg and Susan Wolf, The Adventures of Albert, the Running Bear, Clarion Books, 1982.
Steven Kroll, Amanda the Giggling Ghost, Holiday House, 1980.
Gertrude Norman, The First Book of Music, F. Watts, 1954.
Steven Kroll, Friday the Thirteenth, Holiday House, 1981.
Crescent Dragonwagon, I Hate My Brother Barry, Harper, 1983.
Steven Kroll, Is Milton Missing?, Holiday House, 1975.
Janice Lee Smith, It's Not Easy Being George: Stories about Adam Joshua (and His Dog), HarperCollins Children's Books, 1989.
Mary Calhoun, Jack and the Whoopee Wind, Morrow, 1987. C298
Janice Lee Smith, The Kid Next Door and Other Headaches: Stories about Adam Joshua, Harper, 1984.
Janice Lee Smith, The Monster in the Third Dresser Drawer and Other Stories about Adam Joshua, Harper, 1981.
David A. Adler, My Dog and the Birthday Mystery, Holiday House, 1987.
David A. Alder, My Dog and the Green Sock Mystery, Holiday House, 1986. B174
Marjorie N. Allen, One, Two, Three—Ah-Choo!, Coward, 1980.
Jim Murphy, Rat's Christmas Party, Prentice-Hall, 1979.
Trinka Enell, Roll Over, Rosie, Clarion, 1991.
Janice Lee Smith, The Show-And-Tell War: And Other Stories about Adam Joshua, HarperCollins Children's Books, 1990.
Janice Lee Smith, There's A Ghost in the Coat Room, HarperCollins Children's Books, 1991.
Media Adaptations: The audio version of Timid Timothy's Tongue Twisters (four cassettes and a guide) was issued by Live Oak Media in 1989.
Janice Lee Smith, The Turkey's Side of It: Adam Joshua's Thanksgiving, HarperCollins Children's Books, 1990.
Miriam Anne Bourne, What Is Papa Up To Now?, Coward, 1977.
Sally Cartwright, What's in a Map?, Coward, 1977.
Kathleen Harris, The Wonderful Hay Tumble, Morrow, 1988.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Children's literature, American—20th century.; Children's literature—Manuscripts.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Books.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Illustrations.; Audio cassettes.; Artwork.
Occupations:
Illustrator.; Author.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in 1992 by Mr. Gackenbach.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Books, 1974-1991
  - Alice's Special Room (Box 1)
    - 1991 Houghton Mifflin
    - Letter, 1 sheet
    - Dummy: Cover, pp. 1-32
    - Original art for cover, pp. 1-4/5, 8/9-10/11, 14/15-16/17, 20/21-22/23, 26/27-32.
  - A Bag Full of Pups (Box 2)
    - 1983(reprint) Clarion Books
    - Original art pp. 1-32, 51 sheets
    - Original art for cover, 3 sheets
  - Beauty, Brave and Beautiful (Box 1)
    - 1990 Houghton Mifflin
    - MS, 18 sheets
    - Galleys, 7 sheets
    - Letters, 2 sheets
  - Claude the Dog, A Christmas Story (Box 4)
    - 1974 Clarion Book, The Seabury Press
    - Original art pp. 1-9. 11-32, front and back flaps
  - The Great Staff of Calvin Pitts (Box 1)
    - MS—5 sheets, TS
    - Rough Dummy, 17 sheets
    - Letter, 1 sheet
  - Harvey the Foolish Pig (Box 2)
    - 1988 Houghton Mifflin (Ticknor & Fields?)
    - Dummy and original art for title page, dedication page, pp. 1-32, “The End”
  - Hattie Rabbit (Box 5)
    - 1976 Harper and Row
    - MS—13 sheets, TS
    - Galleys, 4 sheets
    - Cover, Original art pp. 1-32, 51 sheets
  - Is Milton Missing? Steven Kroll (Box 5)
    - 1975 Holiday House
    - Dummies—Cover, pp. 1-32, 18 sheets
    - Letter, 1 sheet
    - Original art cover, front and back flaps, pp. 1-32, 32 sheets
  - Jack and the Whoopee Wind Mary Calhoun (Box 2)
    - 1987 Morrow
    - Original art, 2 boards
  - King Wacky (Box 3)
    - 1984 Crown Publishers
    - Paste ups—11 sheets text, pp. 1-32, 17 sheets
    - Original art cover, pp. 1-32, 54 sheets
  - More from Hound and Bear (Box 3)
    - 1979 Clarion Books, The Seabury Press
    - Dummies—pp. 1-29, 32-48, dust jacket
    - Original art cover, pp. 1-48, 80 sheets
  - My Dog and the Green Sock Mystery David A. Adler (Box 5)
    - 1986 Holiday House
    - Original art pp. 1-32, 51 sheets
    - Letter, 1 sheet
    - Cover art, 3 sheets
  - One—Two—Three—Ah-Choo! Marjorie N. Allen (Box 1)
    - 1980 Coward
    - Letter, 1 sheet
    - 2 Layouts
    - Original art for cover, pp. 2-63, 66 sheets
  - The Perfect Mouse (Box 2)
    - 1984 Macmillan
    - MS—4 sheets TS
    - Dummy pp. 4-32
    - Line drawings, layouts and original art for cover, pp. 1-32, 54 sheets
  - The Pig Who Saw Everything (Box 3)
    - 1978 Clarion Books, The Seabury Press
    - Dummies—pp. 1-40
    - Original art pp. 1-40, 83 sheets
    - Cover, 4 sheets
  - Poppy the Panda (Box 4)
    - 1984 Clarion Books
    - Original art pp. 1-32, 66 sheets
    - Letter, 1 sheet
  - Princess and the Pea (Box 4)
    - 1983 Macmillan
    - Line drawings, layouts and original art for
    - pp. 1, 3-32, 54 sheets
  - Timid Timothy's Tongue Twisters (Box 4)
    - 1989 Live Oaks Media
    - Audio cassette
  - What's Claude Doing? (Box 2)
    - 1984 Clarion Books/Ticknor & Fields
    - Layout and original art for front cover, title page, pp. 2-32, Back cover, unnumbered pages, 56 sheets
  - With Love from Gran (Box 3)
    - 1989 Houghton Mifflin
    - MS, 6 sheets
    - Galleys, 3 sheets
    - Letter, 1 sheet
    - Letter, 1 sheet
    - Original art cover, pp. 1-32, 18 sheets
  - The Wonderful Hay Tumble Kathleen Harris (Box 1)
    - 1988 Morrow
    - Letter, 1 sheet
    - Original art for front/back cover, pp. 1-31, 17 sheets